Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin 1733-1789 Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
- Letters from Benjamin Franklin
  - to ------- ------., 1783 May 22; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    The bearer, Pierre André Gargaz, is the author of a very humane project for establishing a perpetual peace. Is much interested in his behalf. He served twenty years as a galley slave and now requests letters of rehabilitation that he may enjoy, for the rest of his life, the douceurs that state would be attended with.
  - to Comte de Vergennes, 1783 June 3; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Knows Mr. [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.] to be a just man and hopes the favor he asks for an "arrèt de Surséance" may be granted, being persuaded it will be employed to the complete satisfaction of his creditors.
    Printed in works (Bigelow, VIII, 295; Smyth, IX, 47).
  - to [Philippe-Denis] Pierres., 1783 June 10; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Received the copy of the Constitutions. The ratification of the Swedish treaty is arrived so that there is no further obstruction to the publication. Instructions for binding the books.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 523; Bigelow, VIII, 295; Smyth, IX, 47).
  - to Baron [Eric Magnus] de Staël [-Holstein], 1783 June 16; Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has received his letter notifying him of the ratification of the treaty between Sweden and the United States. Expects to receive soon from Congress notice of its ratification also. Will acquaint Congress of the King of Sweden's desire that the United States be represented at his Court by a member of the Franklin family. Congress will, no doubt, do all in its power to be agreeable to a Sovereign who was the first in Europe to offer his friendship to the United States.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 53).
  - to Le Prince de Deux-ponts., 1783 June 17; A.Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Favorable reception likely to be given to the trade with German States. Enumerates articles which America purchases from Europe; reasons why he cannot point out the most reliable business houses in America.
  - to David Hartley., 1783 July 11; Dr. of L. 2p.; Messrs. Franklin and Deane
    They have received from Congress their ratification of the provisional articles [of the Treaty of Peace] and are ready to exchange ratifications with the British Minister. Contrary to one of the articles in which it is stipulated that the British shall, without causing any destruction or carrying away any negroes, withdraw their armies and fleet from the United States, they have been informed that a number of negroes have been carried away from New York. Have instructions from Congress to demand reparation. State that it is agreed that no execution for any debt contracted before the war shall be permitted to be taken out within three years from the day of the signing of the definitive treaty and that no claim of interest shall be admitted.
  - to Chevalier de Laneuville., A.Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Regrets that he did not receive his invitation to celebrate the Anniversary of the American Independence till the day appointed was passed. Assures him, however, that he was not forgot when the company drank to the brave strangers who have hazarded their lives in support of American Liberty.
  - to Prince Bariatinskoy and Mr. De Markoff, Ministers Plenipotentiary from Her Majesty, the Empress of all the Russias, 1783 July; L. 2p.; The American Commissioners?. Passy
    The Empress of Russia and the Emperor of Germany desiring to put a stop to the calamities of war, offered their mediations to the belligerent powers, and as they were informed by Comte de Vergennes that the Kinds of France and England have accepted the mediations of their Imperial Majesties in the Definitive Treaty of Peace about to be concluded between these two powers, they are ready to accept, in behalf of the United States of America, the mediations of their Imperial Majesties in the Definitive Treaty of Peace to be concluded between Great Britain and the United States.
  - Ratification of the Provisional Articles of the Treaty of Peace on the part of His Britannic Majesty, 1783 August 6; D. S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. St. James's
    (Press copy. Attested.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corres. of Am. Rev., Wharton, VI, 631.
  - to Marquis de Vaudreuil, 1783 october 19; A. N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Acknowledges the receipt of the memoirs and promises to communicate them to Congress who doubtless will respect his recommendation of a Consul at the Cape.
  - to [Jean Charles Pierre] Lenoir., 1783 October 31; Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Mme. [John] Jay and himself grateful for what has been done to carry out their intentions with regard to Abigail. Mme. Jay approves the allowance made for her slave's sustenance and will pay all expenses incurred by the latter's imprisonment. Would like to know where she is detained in order to send some one to reason with her. If not successful in doing so will send Abigail back to her native country at the first opportunity.
  - to William Hodgson, 1783 December 10; A. Dr. of L. S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Having represented to the Congress the service rendered to the American prisoners by the Rev. Mr. Wren, he now takes the pleasure of transmitting their thanks, together with a diploma from the College at Princeton, Which he begs him to forward.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 124).
  - to The President of the Continental Congress, [1783.]; A Dr. of Mem. 1 p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
    Memoranda for a letter.
  - to Robert Morris., [1783.]; A. Dr. of Mem.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
  - List of Papers Relating to the Affairs of Georgia., 1771; A. Mem. 1 p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to M. Bariatinskoy, 1783 December 22; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Never heard of the Resolution of Congress which he mentions, and doubts much of its existence; nor has he heard anything of the supposed decision in Council at Versailles concerning it. Understands that a number of American officers have agreed to form themselves into a society for the purpose of relieving their poor widows and orphans hereafter.
  - Rough Draft of a Flying Machine, [1783]; A. Drawing. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to Samuel Chase, 1784 January 6; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Relative to the loss of his ship. Is not enough acquainted with teh French laws and customs to inform him what claim the widw of M. Le Vaché, may have upon his property. Relative to teh validity of marriages by Protestant ministers.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 53; Bigelow, VIII, 427; Smyth, IX, 152)
  - to M. Creuze [?], 1784. February 14.; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Received his three letters relating to aerostatic machines and the means of directing their motion. Communicated the letters to the committee which was appointed by the Acedamy of Sciences to consider that subject.
  - to M. [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy, 1784 February 25; A. L. S. 1p. (Copy); Franklin, Benjamin
    Encloses a letter and sundry papers which he received from Mr. [Anthony George] Eckhardt, of Utrecht, a most ingenious mechanician. IF he can do him any service, he requests him to do so; also to show to [Joseph Michel] Montgolfier what Mr. Eckhardt says of balloons.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 173).
  - to Comte de Vergennes., 1784 February 26.; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Mr. [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.] having amicably arranged his affairs with the bulk of his creditors he now joins his request for an "arrêt de surséance" that he may be secured against the small number remaining who aim at forcing him to favor them to the prejudice of the others.
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, VIII, 451; Smyth, IX, 173).
  - to ---- ----., 1784 March 4; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Appointment of consuls does not belong to him. Thinks that whenever one is appointed for Dunkirk, it will be Mr. [Francis] Coffyn, who for seven years has constantly taken care of and relieved the poor prisoners escaping from England, without any compensation.
  - to Comte de Vergennes, 1784 March 5; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Received his letter respecting the necessity of producing legal proof of the arrangements made with the creditors mentioned in Mr. [Jonathan] Williams's state of affairs, and sends herewith the original of those arrangements for his inspection.
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, VIII, 454; Smyth, IX, 176).
  - to Abbé Morellet, 1784 March 16; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    No one else has seen the paper, and it will probably not appear until after his decease, if it does then; his opinion of the translation.
  - to ----- Mazue., 1784 March 19; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Acknowledging M. Mazue's letter; believes it is yet too early to put such a project into execution; the culture of wheat is more profitable and certain, and in exchange the wines of Europe can be procured cheaper than the cost of home production.
  - to La Sabliére de La Condamine., 1784 March 19; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Acknowledging his favor of the 8th inst. Thinks maladies caused by obstruction may be helped by electricity; doubts the existence of animal magnetism; fears the new method will prove a delusion.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 75; Bigelow, VIII, 460) and in Hale's Franklin in France, II, 293.
  - to ----- Milee l'ainé, 1784 March 19; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has no orders or authority to encourage any person to go to America by promising lands or other favors from Government; the enclosed printed paper describing the country will perhaps convince the young man that he is better where he is.
  - to Mme. Brillon, 1784 March 31; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sends her one of his "serious pleasantries." Hopes it will amuse her and that she will recompense him by playing a Christmas carol and the "March of the Insurgents."
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 191), and in Proc. Am. Philos. Soc., 1901, XL, 113.
  - to Mme. Brillon, 1784 April 8; A.L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sent her, by M. [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy, the "Notice for those who wish to remove to America" and "Remarks on politeness amongst the savages." Sends with this note several other little pieces printed in his house at Passy. With "The Deformed and Handsome Leg" and the "Morals of Chess" previously presented to her, this completes the collection of his "bagatelles" printed at Passy. Is sorry to hear M. Brillon is suffering from gout. Sends him some advice given him by "La Goutte" herself which he did not follow but which he hopes will be useful to a fellow-sufferer.
    Printed in Proc. Am. Philos. Soc., XL., 96.
  - to Le Ray de Chaumont, 1784 May 2; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sorry to learn that Mr. [Ferdinand] Grand declines acting as an arbitrator, because if it must be settled by others than themselves it is best it should be done by their common friends. Has always been ready to submit the matters in dispute, but knowing the difficult situation of his affairs he forbore from pressing the point, believing that so soon as his affairs should be arranged it would not be difficult for them to adjust their accounts themselves without the help of any arbitrator and proposes that they should try that experiment.
  - to Memorandum, 1784 May 10; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Notes upon M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont's accounts.
  - 1784 May 28, D.S. Le Ray de Chaumont, B[enjamin] Franklin. 1p.; Benjamin Franklin and Le Ray de Chaumont. Passy
    Declaration of approval to the decision of M. [Ferdinand] Grand as Arbitrator of their disputed accounts. The latter found that M. de Chaumont was indebted to Franklin in a sum of over 35,000 livres (or francs) but as Congress owed M. de Chaumont a much larger amount for merchandise and supplies furnished to Gen. [Benjamin] Lincoln, Franklin agreed to allow him to retain the above sum as part payment of the account due him by Congress. They both agree to consider everything settled between them personally and release each other from all claims and pecuniary obligations whatsoever.
  - to [Comte] de Campomanes., 1784 June 5; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Power of an individual to do good. Two erroneous opinions prevalent in Europe which is injurious to National felicity, but which is not found in America. Perepetuation of families by estates.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 98; Bigelow, VIII, 497; Smyth, IX, 221).
  - to Thomas Barclay., 1784 July 6; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Requests him to peruse the enclosed letter of the Marquis de Castries, with the Resolutions of Congress respecting the division of the prize-money, and to favor him with his opinion. Also desires to know whether there have been any decisions upon a similar case in America or any subsequent rules given by Congress.
  - to Messrs. Sears and Smith, 1784 August 4; A.L.S. 2p. (Press copy.); Franklin, Benjamin
    Duty on slaves imported into the French Islands. Does not see any possibility of their avoiding the payment.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 119; Bigelow, IX, 23; Smyth, IX, 249).
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1784 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Requests him to deliver the enclosed pacquet from M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard which contains two letters of recommendation which he gave the Count [Mirabeau] at M. Veillard's request, one to Dr. [Richard] Price and the other to Mr. [Benjamin] Vaughan. [Friederich Anton] Mesmer's complaint to the Parliament of their report. M. Mesmer will be obliged to disclose all.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 170).
  - to ----- de la Valinière., 1784 September 12; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    The Catholic religion is allowed in all the States of the Union; but no lands are given away free. Has no knowledge of the establishment of Bishops referred to, but knows there is such an establishment in Canada and a suffragan bishop in Maryland. Congress has allotted no fund for persons wishing to emigrate to the United States.
  - to P[ierre] Roussille., 1784 September 12; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Should make his claim in America for wages and share of prize-money due him by the privateer "Boston," as that vessel was fitted out there. Advises him to send his claim and proof to the French Consul at Philadelphia.
  - to Jacques Chapel., 1784 September 12; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Cannot give him a letter of introduction to the United States Minister at London, as none has been appointed yet. Has been away from London too long to be able to tell him what are the most reliable business houses in that city.
  - to Hall and Sellers., 1784 September 13; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Recommending M. Prosper Mouret, a printer.
  - to [Prosper] Mouret., 1784 September 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sends him the desired letters of recommendation but would not advise him to go to North America. Thinks he would get on better in the French West Indies where there are printing houses and where French is the language of the country.
  - to W[illia]m T[emple] Franklin. London., 1784 September 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has suffered somewhat by his riding in a carriage to Auteuil; will not repeat the experiment again. Procured a Sauf conduit for B[enjamin Franklin Bache], he leaves to-morrow; Mr. [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.] will supply his place.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 272).
  - to John Jay, 1784 September 15; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has heard of Mr. [John] Jay's safe arrival home. Mr. [David] Hartley has been recalled. Messrs. [John] Adams and [Thomas] Jefferson have arrived.
  - to W[illia]m T[emple] Franklin, 1784 October 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Rebukes him for not writing since September 7. Thinks his father should write if his fever returned.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 274).
  - to William Carmichael., 1784 October 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Incloses the Count d'Aranda's answer to his last letter. Has not replied to it yet. Glad to learn that Mr. [Diego de] Gardoqui is sent to America. Relative to the scizure of James Hartwell, of Salem, with a cargo of tobacco, by the officers of the Spanish Inquisition. Requests him to take proper steps for his release and the restitution of his property.
  - to W[illia]m T[emple] Franklin, London., 1784 October 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Glad to hear that Mrs. [Mary] Hewson resolved to come to Paris. Consents to his remaining in England to the end of the month on condition that he visits Chilbolton and brings him word of the welfare of that dear [Shipley] family. Saw an advertisement in an English paper of cast iron tiles for covering houses. Asks him to bring him one as a sample and to ascertain the price. Would like to cover his house in Philadelphia with them.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 277).
  - to D. Inarre., 1784 November 10; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sends him a pamphlet of advice to intending emigrants to North America. Does not doubt he could make a good living by farming in Pennsylvania. On account of his age and family, however, would not advise him to undertake such a long journey to settle amongst strangers.
  - to D. Inarre., 1784 November 10.; L.S. 1p.; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sends him a pamphlet of advice to intending emigrants to North America. Does not doubt he could make a good living by framing in Pennsylvania. On account of his age and family, however, would not advise him to undertake such a long journey to settle amongst strangers.
  - to Messrs. Witel and Pauche., 1784 November 15; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has some doubts whether he will find the book-selling and printing business sufficiently profitable to support three families. Thinks if they can add to the sale of books the different manufactures of his country, the profit may be considerable. Incloses a pamphlet which will give him some information respecting his country.
  - to Messrs. Witel and Pauche., 1784 November 15; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 279).
  - to Monte Brav., 1784 November 22; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Too much a stranger to every dispute on mesmerism to consent to have his name appear directly or indirectly, except in the report of the Commissioners.
  - to M. Desfours., 1784 November 23; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Did not receive the plan referred to in his letter. Has no authority to grant or refuse the commission he desires. Can only forward his request to Congress and communicate its reply to him.
  - to Abbé de Charmois., 1784 November 23; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Cannot give a free passage to America to Francisque Sube, as there is no vessel belonging to the United States in any port in France, and, as peace has been concluded, there will probably be none for sometime.
  - to Thomas Jefferson., 1784 November 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Relative to the habit people have of asking assistance in whatever they do.
    (In duplicate. Press copy.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 151; Bigelow, IX, 70; Smyth, IX, 281).
  - to ----- Marioge., 1784 November 23; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has not been directed by Congress to send anyone to the United States to establish factories there. No special inducements are held out to draw foreigners there. Should reflect well before deciding to go with his family such a distance to live amongst strangers. Sends him a little printed notice on the subject of emigration to America.
  - to M. Lafont., 1784 November 24; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Cannot advise him to undertake a long and costly journey to establish a medical practice in America where he would be without friends and unable to speak the language of the country. Thinks he would do better to go to the French islands.
  - to Mme. Brillon., 1784 November 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Congratulating her on the birth of the baby.
    Printed in Proc. Am. Philos. Soc., XL, 105, and in Putnam's Monthly, Oct., 1906, 37.
  - The Savages of North America., [1784.]; Diss. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Printed in Works (Sparks, II, 453; Bigelow, IX, 25).
  - 1784, D. 23p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Alphabetical list of Americans who escaped from English prisons and were furnished money by the American Commissioners to return home.
  - Memorandum., A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Lies respecting America in general to encourage the making war on them, and lies since the peace to encourage a renewal of the war.
  - to The Ambassador of Sweden., A. Dr. of N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Making an appointment to meet him.
  - to ----- -----., Mem. 5p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Concerning the different kinds of currency in use in the United States and their value. Explaining the exchage and banking system.
  - to ----- -----., [1784.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Commercial and financial affairs. Congratulations upon quitting public life.
    (First part missing. Press copy.)
  - to Mme. Brillon, A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    She is too sensitive and kind-hearted and he gives her some advice. Ingratitude is a terrible evil, but it only hurts the ungrateful. If those whom she has benefited prove ungrateful, it is their crime and should not disturb her. Those who have heaped injuries on her in return for benefits have only lowered themselves and become inferior to her. She should not seek to be revenged on them; time will prove the rectitude of her conduct and those who have slandered her will seek her friendship. Hopes she will be able to make out his meaning in spite of the defects and clumsiness of his style in French.
    Printed in Putnam's Magazine, Dec., 1906, 315.
  - to ------ Bedtinger, 1785 January 2; L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Regrets to be unable to appoint M. Dupüis as Consul for the United States at Havre. Mr. [Thomas] Barclay, the Consul-General, can alone make such appointments and he is obliged to select citizens of the United States.
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand., 1785 January 9; L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Relative to a proposition respecting the payment of the interest on the Holland Loan, and other financial concerns.
    Printed in the Diplom. Corres. 1783- 1789 Wharton, II, 40.
  - Memorandum., 1785 April 12; Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Blank form of bill of exchange payable to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to ------- Brillon, 1785 February 16; L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sends him an extract from letter written to him by Bache and Shee with reference to the claim fo M. Thomas against that firm for goods shipped to them at Philadelphia.
    Extract from M. Thomas's reply addressed to Abbé de St. Non and dated at Florence, March 11, 1785, with reference to his claim against Bache and Shee.
  - to Pierre Vernier., 1785 February 19; Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Congress in taking steps to redeem the contracts issued by the Loan Office and to insure payment of interest thereon, which was interrupted for a time. Neither the principal nor interest, however, can be paid without the contracts being produced. Holders of the contracts should not have sent them to Europe, where they are of no value. Advises him to send the contracts he has back to America to some merchant or to M. [Pierre François] Barbé de Marbois, French Consul at Philadelphia.
    (Mostly in French.)
  - to Count de Windisch-Grâtz, 1785 February 22; Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Cannot but approve of the article enclosed in his letter. Will forward any copies of it to America which he may send.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 290).